In the first years
of the 21st century...
a third world war broke out.
Those of us who survived
knew mankind
could never survive...
a fourth.
That our own volatile natures
could simply
no longer be risked.
So we have created
a new arm of the law...
the Grammaton Cleric,
whose sole task it is
to seek out and eradicate
the true source
of man's inhumanity to man,
his ability
to feel.
Police!
You know what to do.
Get down!
Cleric. Lights out.
Maybe more than a dozen inside.
When the door's down,
blow the bulbs.
Go.
[gunfire]
[silence]
[whispering]
- This is it.
- Where?
There.
It's real.
Burn it.
Why didn't you just leave it
for the Evidentiary Team to log?
They miss things sometimes.
I thought I'd take it down
myself, get it done properly.
How long, Preston,
until all this is gone?
Until we've burned
every last bit of it?
Resources are tight.
We'll get it all eventually.
Libria, I congratulate you.
At last, peace reigns
in the heart of man.
At last, war is but a word
whose meaning fades
from our understanding.
At last... we... are... home.
Librians, there is a disease
in the heart of man.
Its symptom is hate.
Its symptom is anger.
Its symptom is rage.
Its symptom is war.
The disease is human emotion.
But Libria, I congratulate you.
For there is a cure
for this disease.
At the cost of the dizzying
highs of human emotion,
we have suppressed
its abysmal lows.
And you, as a society,
have embraced this cure.
Prozium.
Now we are at peace
with ourselves
and humankind is one.
War has gone. Hate, a memory.
We are our own conscience now
and it is this conscience
that guides us to rate EC-10
for emotional content
all those things that might
tempt us to feel again
and destroy them!
Librians, you have won!
Against all odds
and your own natures,
you have survived.
[bleeping]
Every time we come from
the Nethers to the city,
it reminds me
of why we do what we do.
It does?
I beg your pardon?
It does.
The following items have been
rated EC-10 Condemned.
Seven works of two-dimensional
illustrated material,
seven discs of musical content,
twenty interactive
strategy computer programs.
Thank you for coming, Cleric.
I assume you know who I am.
Yes, sir, of course.
You are Vice-Council Dupont,
of the Third Counciliary of
the Tetragrammaton. Father's voice.
I am told that you were
very nearly a prodigal student,
knowing almost instantly
if someone is feeling.
I have a good record, sir.
Why do you imagine that is, Cleric?
I'm not sure, Vice-Council.
Somehow...
I'm able, on some level,
to sense how an offender thinks,
to put myself in their position.
If you had ceased your interval.
If you were a sense offender.
I suppose you could
say that, sir.
- You're a family man, Cleric?
- Yes, sir. A boy and a girl.
The boy's in the Monastery
on path to becoming a cleric.
Good. And the mother?
My spouse was incinerated for
sense offence four years ago.
- By yourself?
- No, sir. By another.
How did you feel about that?
I'm sorry,
I don't fully understand, sir.
How did you feel?
I didn't feel anything.
Really? How is it that
you came to miss it?
I...
I've asked myself that same
question, sir. I don't know.
A nearly unforgivable lapse, Cleric.
I trust you'll be more vigilant
in the future.
Yes, sir.
Every time we come from
the Nethers to the city,
it reminds me
of why we do what we do.
It does?
Every time we come from
the Nethers to the city,
it reminds me
of why we do what we do.
It does?
It does.
Prosecutorial evidence
for A&R 136890.
I need it.
It was late this afternoon.
May not have showed up
in the records yet.
Nothing logged and nothing
pending under that entry.
It was an item brought in
by Grammaton Erroll Partridge.
Check again.
Cleric Partridge has not
entered anything in for weeks.
You're mistaken.
It was a book of some kind.
Cleric.
There's nothing.
Thank you.
He's been into the Nether
every night for two weeks.
We assumed
it was enforcement-related.
You always knew.
"But I, being poor,
have only my dreams."
"I've spread my dreams
under your feet."
"Tread softly,
because you tread on my dreams."
I assume you dream, Preston.
I'll do what I can
to see they go easy on you.
We both know they never go easy.
- Then I'm sorry.
- No, you're not.
You don't even know the meaning.
It's just a vestigial word
for a feeling you've never felt.
Don't you see, Preston?
It's gone.
Everything that makes us
what we are, traded away.
There's no war. No murder.
- What is it you think we do?
- No. You've been with me.
You've seen how it can be,
the jealousy, the rage.
A heavy cost.
I pay it gladly.
Don't.
You and your partner were close?
I hope you're as pleased
to be assigned me
as I am the placement.
I was told this would be
a career-making advancement.
I'm like you, Cleric. Intuitive.
Sometimes I know what a person's
feeling before they know it.
Cleric.
I could only hope
one day to be as...
uncompromising as you.
Good night.
The later 20th century
saw the fortuitous
and simultaneous rise
of two synergistic political
and psychological sciences.
The first, the revolutionary
precept of the hate crime.
- John.
- Yes.
I saw Bobbie Taylor
crying today.
He didn't know, but I saw.
Do you think I should report him?
Unquestionably.
...the single inescapable fact
that mankind united
with infinitely greater purpose
in pursuit of war
than he ever did
in pursuit of peace.
[Partridge] "But I, being poor,
have only my dreams."
"I've spread my dreams
under your feet."
"Tread softly, because
you tread on my dreams."
Viviana Preston, don't move!
Don't move! Comply! Comply!
- Stop where you are!
- Get down! Get down!
Don't shoot.
This is a lawful entry.
We have a warrant for your
wife's arrest for sense offence.
Hey! Get her!
Get her off him now!
Remember me.
Awaken to triumph again
in the face of yet another day.
Another step...
[son] What are you doing?
I said, what are you doing?
I accidentally dropped
my morning interval.
I took it out
before I brushed my teeth.
I never take it out
before I brush my teeth.
Then you'll go by Equilibrium,
log the loss
and get a replacement.
Yes. Of course.
Your new partner called.
He'll pick you up at ten for the A&R.
I hope you don't mind.
I took the liberty of telling him
you would be at Equilibrium
replacing your dose.
No, of course not.
That was the right thing to do.
[girl stirs food]
Stop that.
Due to terrorist activity,
this site is temporarily closed.
Proceed to the Equilibrium
Centre in Sector 8-A.
Due to terrorist activity,
this site is temporarily closed...
[hooting]
More than punctual, Cleric. Hop in.
How are the lines? I'm surprised
you could get your interval
and get out so quickly.
No, they're fine today.
Maybe I'll drop by later
and get my interval adjusted.
You expecting resistance?
That's something you'll find
about me. I'm a wary person.
Cautious by nature.
Always expecting the worst.
- You cannot do this.
- Tetragrammaton.
There's nothing we can't do.
How long have you been
off the dose? Look at you.
Look at you!
Look at you.
The mirror's frame's illegal.
Destroy it.
You're gonna burn it, aren't you?
Eventually.
However, you couldn't have
accumulated this by yourself.
It'll all be sorted and examined.
We'll discover
who your confederates are.
We need her.
- What's your name?
- O'Brien. Mary.
Well, Mary, you can either wait
and tell the Technicians
of the Palace of Justice
or you can tell me now.
Who are your friends?
I'm wondering
if you have any idea at all
what that word means - friend.
There's nothing you don't feel?
How about guilt?
Let me ask you something.
Why are you alive?
I'm alive...
I live...
to safeguard the continuity
of this great society,
to serve Libria.
It's circular. You exist
to continue your existence.
What's the point?
What's the point
of your existence?
To feel. Because you've never
done it, you can never know it.
But it's as vital as breath.
And without it, without love,
without anger, without sorrow,
breath is just a clock... ticking.
Then I have no choice
but to remand you
to the Palace of Justice for processing.
Processing.
You mean execution, don't you?
The gun katas. Through analysis
of recorded gunfights,
the Cleric has determined
that the distribution
of antagonists in any gun battle
is a statistically predictable element.
The gun kata treats the gun
as a total weapon,
each new position representing
a maximum kill zone,
inflicting maximum damage
on the maximum number of opponents,
while keeping the defender clear
of statistically traditional
trajectories of return fire.
By the rote mastery of this art,
your firing efficiency
will rise by no less than 120%.
The difference of a 63%
increased lethal proficiency
makes the master of the gun katas
an adversary not to be taken lightly.
[Mary] Without love,
breath is just a clock... ticking.
[rapid heartbeat]
Prozium - the great nepenthe.
Opiate of our masses,
glue of our great society.
Salve and salvation,
it has delivered us from pathos,
from sorrow, the deepest chasms
of melancholy and hate.
With it we anaesthetise grief,
annihilate jealousy,
obliterate rage.
Those sister impulses
toward joy, love and elation
are anaesthetised in stride,
except as fair sacrifice.
For we embrace Prozium
in its unifying fullness
and all that it has done
to make us great.
- Good morning, Cleric.
- Good morning.
...intrinsically humans
as creatures of the earth
were drawn inherently
always back to one thing: war.
And thus we seek to correct
not the symptom,
but the disease itself.
We have sought
to shrug off individuality,
replacing it with conformity.
Replacing it with sameness, with unity,
allowing each man, woman and child
in this great society
to lead identical lives.
The concept of identical
viable construction
allows each of us to head
confidently into each moment...
What are you doing?
I'm rearranging my desk.
You didn't like the way it was before?
I had no feelings about it.
I'm merely attempting to optimise.
Sense offenders holed up in the Nether.
We estimate 50 men, sir.
Intelligence tells us
they're all fully armed.
This is the group that bombed
the Prozium factories.
- You clean, we'll sweep.
- Yes, sir.
Go, go, go, go! Go!
Cover me. I'm going in.
Nice grab, Cleric.
Ludwig van Beethoven.
[Beethoven symphony starts]
Cleric, why didn't you leave
that for the Evidentiary Team
to collect and log?
They miss things sometimes.
I'm gonna take it in myself,
make sure it gets done properly.
You know, Preston,
if we keep burning
all this contraband,
eventually there won't be
anything left to burn.
What'll there be for men like us?
Sir! We got something out back.
They were defended by women
and children. We put them down.
This isn't the first time
we've seen this.
Why do they keep these animals?
Do they... Do they eat 'em?
- What do you want me to do?
- Exterminate them, of course.
- All right, let's do it.
- No.
What's wrong, Cleric?
Nothing.
Hey! Grab it. Grab it!
Sir, toss it back in.
I'll finish it off.
- Give it to me, sir.
- Give it to him.
He'll finish it.
[dog whines]
Wait!
It seems to me that...
at least some of these animals
ought to be tested for disease.
If there's an epidemic in
the Nethers, it's best we know.
I don't quite follow your logic, Cleric.
They were Resistance. They could
have led us to the Underground.
But instead of interrogation,
they were slaughtered.
But given the circumstances,
the Father has decreed
that there will be no more
process for sense offenders.
They are to be shot on sight
or incinerated without trial.
It's counter to law.
You're a member of the Council...
It is not the will of the Council.
It is the will of Father and he is law.
Sir...
without the logic of process,
is it not just mayhem?
What we have worked so hard
to eradicate?
You must understand, Preston,
that while you and even I
may not always agree with it,
it is not the message
that is important.
It is our obedience to it.
Father's will.
Call it faith. You have it, I assume.
Yes. I have it.
Good.
Confiscated evidence X-23-T-45.
Mary O'Brien.
Cleric John Preston passing into
the Nether. Enforcement-related.
Thank you, sir.
I don't know what else to do with you.
Go on. Go on.
Go!
[dog yelps]
[barks]
Fine. But you're going back
in the trunk.
OK.
Here.
Step away from the vehicle.
This is your last warning.
Identification.
Cleric. I'm here on official...
- Identification!
- It's in my coat.
- Where's the coat? Where is it?
- I don't have it.
Unidentified individuals
are subject to destruction.
You're making a mistake. I'm
a Grammaton Cleric First Class.
- We'll search your vehicle.
- There's nothing in it.
Search it.
- Clear, sir.
- Keys to the trunk.
I'm trying to tell you I have
a predawn combustion to witness...
This is a waste of my time.
My name is John Preston.
I'm the highest-ranking cleric...
Wait!
Stand off.
I'm sorry.
I didn't recognise you, sir.
That's OK. Just doing your job.
Thank you. We'll escort you back
to the gate.
- Thanks.
- [dog yelps]
Animals.
The Nether's full of 'em.
Sounds like it came from your trunk.
Impossible. Just give me my keys.
I'll be on my way.
Captain, I'm asking you one last time.
Don't do this.
- Down on your knees!
Shoot him!
Fuck!
What? Shit!
Shoot him, shoot him, shoot him!
[grunts]
Always practising, Cleric.
I guess that's why you're the best.
Maybe I'm just better.
Something on your mind?
- Why do you ask?
- The intuitive arts.
It's my job to know
what you're thinking.
So, then, what am I thinking?
About the murders
in the Nether last night.
And if they know who did it.
Am I close?
So tell me, do they know?
There are theories.
I have one of two of my own,
but at the moment
they're premature.
I'm glad it happened.
- Why?
- Now Father and the Council
have to create an acceleration
in the crackdown on offenders.
Whoever did it, all they accomplished
was a quicker end to the Resistance.
It's gonna be a massacre, Cleric.
I came to tell you there's a raid
in the Nether. Sector 7.
So get ready.
That door behind you.
Go.
Go, damn you!
Get out of here.
If you don't, you're dead.
- He'll shoot us in the back.
- I'd shoot you in the face. Go.
Damn you! Follow me. Now!
Let's go.
Prisoners and apprehendees
are to be put down.
Look out!
What's happening?
We heard gunshots.
- Go!
- What are you doing?
They're Resistance fighters. Cleric!
He's a sense offender!
[shouting]
What is this?
- What are you doing?
- Nicely done, Cleric.
You drive them into the trap.
I close it.
The very definition of teamwork.
Don't you think?
Why don't you take the honours
of the execution, Cleric?
These people should be taken
for clinical interrogation.
Father's rulings are quite clear.
Offenders are to be shot on sight.
They have valuable information.
They can be put to better use...
Cleric.
If your weapon's low, please use mine.
No.
I think, in the end,
it'll be better if you have it.
- Captain.
- Yes, sir. Firing positions!
Ready!
Aim!
Fire!
- Sir.
- Yes, Cleric.
You asked me to be an instrument
against the Resistance.
I'm ready. Today.
I wish to show my faith.
I wish with your permission
to locate the Underground
once and for all.
To destroy it.
- To destroy it.
- Good. Do it.
I'm so... so very sorry.
These are the possessions he had
on him at the time of death.
The legal ones will be burned with him.
Good.
Erroll Partridge.
It's supposed to mean something?
He was a Grammaton Cleric
First Class. You knew him.
News bulletin. I'm a sense offender.
I don't hang round much
with the Cleric.
I wanna know about him.
Well, I suggest you go ask him,
but I understand that he's dead.
Killed by your friends
at the Tetragrammaton.
Not by my friends. By me.
You were lovers.
And thus it is in the writing
of the Father
that we find our greatest...
Good afternoon, sir.
What will it be for you?
The latest copy of The Insensate?
Revised edition of the Manifesto?
Erroll Partridge.
What do you know about him?
- I beg your pardon?
- Everyone out now.
I'm gonna ask you one more time.
Erroll Partridge.
What do you know about him?
I'm sure this must be
some mistake.
- You're an offender.
- I'm not.
No? Then why are you
so scared of me?
You will tell me everything
you know about Erroll Partridge,
or I will have you taken
to the Hall of Destruction
for summary combustion.
- I really don't know...
- Speak!
He'd come in here
with a fella named Jurgen.
- Why?
- That's all I know, I swear.
Interesting.
We've been watching you, Preston.
You're Jurgen.
You're feeling.
Do you know why you came?
Welcome to the Underground.
Polygraph.
It detects fluctuations
of human emotion.
We have to be sure.
Mary.
You're carrying in your pocket
a ribbon sprayed with her scent.
You breathe it in sometimes when
you think there's no one to see.
But what you feel...
could only be satisfied
by folding yourself into her.
She's scheduled for combustion.
Tomorrow.
I know.
You know, I was like you.
But the first thing you learn
about emotion
is that it has its price.
A complete paradox.
But without restraint,
without control,
emotion is chaos.
- How is that...
- The difference is that
when we want to feel, we can.
It's just that... some of us...
have to forego that luxury
so that the rest can have it.
Some very few of us have
to force ourselves not to feel.
Like me.
Like you.
What can I do?
You can kill Father.
[truck horn beeps]
Cleric John Preston,
you are to come with us immediately.
- Cleric Preston.
- Sir.
I've heard
the most disturbing rumour.
- Rumour, sir?
- Yes.
A rumour maintaining
that one of us, one of the Cleric,
has secretly taken it
upon himself to cease his dose.
That one of our elite number
is actually feeling.
Feeling, sir?
Are you playing with me, Cleric?
[guns cock]
No, sir.
This person, I'm told,
is actually attempting
to contact the Resistance.
Now, tell me,
if you would be so kind,
how exactly have you been
making use of your time of late?
Attempting to contact
the Resistance, sir.
Attempting?
How is it that you intend
to expose this traitor
if all you do is attempt?
You're absolutely 100% right, sir.
Of course I am.
The Cleric is the final line of defence.
If the Resistance
compromises it, we are doomed.
Father is doomed.
I will redouble my effort, sir,
to locate the Resistance,
to find this traitor
and bring them all
to the Council's fair justice.
Do it.
What are you doing?
I, uh...
I was checking
to make sure you've been...
taking your interval.
And are you satisfied?
Yes, I am.
Good night, then.
I don't understand.
My execution's set.
Why are you here?
[bleeping]
Aren't you going to dose?
My God.
What...
What'll you do?
I don't know.
- Fifty sweepers, maybe more.
- What about an audience?
Father's never given a single
audience since the upheaval.
They've trained you
to fight these kind of odds.
Even if I could...
Even if I could make it through,
what guarantee is there
it would accomplish anything,
anything would be different?
Our network is larger
than you could imagine.
The instant word comes
that Father is dead,
bombs will be set off at the Prozium
clinics and factories.
If we can succeed in disrupting
the supply for even one day,
one day, our cause will be won
by human nature itself.
What about war? There would be
cruelties that are gone.
Replaced by the Tetragrammaton?
Will you do it?
Yes.
Can you?
I don't know.
Don't... Seeing her one last time
will only make it harder
to do what you have to do.
File footage.
Viviana Preston.
Sentence and incineration.
- Auditory.
- Viviana Preston,
for ceasing your interval,
for the crime of feeling,
you will suffer annihilation
in the city furnaces.
You will be taken there
immediately and you will burn.
Has the incineration gone through?
It's going through now. Hey!
Machine turbines priming.
- I need to speak to this woman.
- You're too late.
If we force the door now,
the turbines will explode
at street level.
...clear the area immediately.
All unauthorized personnel,
clear the area immediately.
Turbines primed.
Fire in ten seconds,
nine seconds, eight seconds,
seven seconds, six seconds,
five seconds, four seconds,
three seconds, two seconds...
Turbines... fire.
Cleric John Preston.
You are under arrest.
This man, this senior cleric,
has ceased the dose.
He is feeling.
He is the worm
that has been eating at the core
of our great society.
And I... I have brought him
for your justice.
I told you I'd make my career
with you, Preston.
Vice-Council, this man is guilty
of consorting with sense offenders,
of having relations with a female,
of sense crime itself.
Dispatch a team to his quarters
to search for unused Prozium.
If you'll run the trace record
on his sidearm,
you will find it was he
who was with the sweeper team
when they were murdered.
Cleric, I assume
you have something to say to me.
I know...
it's hard to believe...
that a cleric of the Tetragrammaton
could turn his back
on everything he's been taught,
become associated
with the Resistance,
even becoming a champion
in its Underground.
But it's true.
I promised
I would bring you that man.
And I have.
- Cleric Brandt.
- Sir.
The trace shows
that it was your gun
in the Nether with the sweepers.
That's impossible.
This is wrong.
I think, in the end,
it'll be better if you have it.
He switched them.
See, I have his gun now.
Of course you do. You took it
when you arrested me.
What?
Take him to the Hall
of Destruction for combustion.
Wait, wait, wait, wait!
I can explain this.
I'm not feeling.
He is the one who's feeling.
This is a mistake.
Of course, since a complaint
has been lodged,
law and the letter
is that I allow a team
to carry out the search
of your premises.
Do you think that's entirely
necessary or am I being too...
exacting?
As you say, sir,
it's the law and the letter.
And it doesn't disturb you
in the least
that your colleague
is going to his end?
The only thing that disturbs me,
sir, is that
I am Father's instrument against
the Underground, and yet...
I've never had the honour
of meeting him.
You know that Father never
grants an audience to anyone.
Even to the man who brings him
the Resistance?
Just a formality. The search team
will be up momentarily.
Excellent. I have nothing to hide.
The search team's already inside, sir.
Excellent.
[son] Looking for something?
If I were you, I'd be more
careful... in the future.
- How long?
- Since Mom.
- And Lisa?
- Of course.
- How did you know?
- You forget.
It's my job to know
what you're thinking.
Then you know
what I'm gonna do now.
You have a message
for the Vice-Council?
It's done.
I've located the Resistance.
Come now. You'll have them all.
Do not address Father
unless first addressed by him.
Avoid eye contact.
If you should break
his personal security zone,
you will be immediately put down
by snipers. Is that understood?
You'll be required to surrender
your firearm, of course.
- And then there's the test.
- Test?
Yes. You didn't imagine
we would risk exposing Father
to even such
a dedicated servant as yourself
without first
having him tested, did you?
Please.
Cleric, your weapon, please.
Here.
Sit.
We'll start with
a test question first.
More of a riddle, actually.
What would you say
is the easiest way
to get a weapon away
from a Grammaton Cleric?
You ask him for it.
I told you I'd make
my career with you, Cleric.
Preston. Brandt's job was simple.
To make you feel like you'd won,
to make you feel safe.
For years,
I tried to infiltrate an agent
into the Underground,
until it hit me.
In order to pass undetected
into their midst,
in order to be trusted by them,
my provocateur
would have to think like them,
and would have to feel like them.
But where to find such a man?
A man with the capacity to feel
who didn't yet know it.
But... we've never met.
No?
Don't look so surprised.
Why should Father be more real
than any other political puppet?
The real Father died years ago.
The Council elected me
to pursue his paternal tradition.
And you, Preston,
the supposed saviour
of the Resistance,
are now its destroyer.
And along with them
you've given me yourself.
Calmly. Coolly.
Entirely without incident.
No.
- [long bleep]
- Oh.
Shit.
Not without incident.
I'm coming.
You really should learn to knock.
How did it feel, Preston?
[growls]
Mind the uniform, Cleric.
I plan to be wearing it
for a long time.
Be careful, Preston.
You're treading on my dreams.
No!
Wait! Wait!
Look at me. Look at me.
I'm life. I live, I breathe.
I feel.
Now that you know it,
can you really take it?
Is it really worth the price?
I pay it gladly.
The following items have been
rated EC-10 Condemned.
...conquest of the known world,
Alexander the Great
slaughtered more than
one million human beings.
Three centuries later,
purely out of jealousy,
Gaius Germanicus Caligula
murdered his own sister,
impregnated with his own child.
...rated EC-10...
...rated Condemned, destroy...